cp:

+1(732)318-9650

hbahamonde@tulane.edu

Center for Inter-American Policy & Research Tulane University Richardson Hall 205 Richardson, New Orleans, LA 70118

CV last updated: April 24, 2018.

Download latest CV here.

Career Objective

I want to help institutions (big or small) to reach their goals by incorporating my experience as an academic. By bringing my analytical skills, and excellent interpersonal relationships, I am interested in both leading teams and collaborating with others. My ideal institution lets its employees be innovative, goal-oriented and creative.

Education

Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey-New Brunswick

Ph.D. Political Science, September 2012–May 2017.

Dissertation: "State Capacities in Latin America: Structural Transformations, Elite Competition, and Fiscal Development (1850-2010)."

Committee: Robert Kaufman (chair), Daniel Kelemen, Douglas Blair, Paul Poast (University of Chicago).

Fields: Comparative Politics and Quantitative Methodology.

Catholic University of Chile-Santiago.

B.A. Political Science, 2005–2009.

Academic Employment

Universidad de O'Higgins, Rancagua, Chile

Assistant Professor, July 2018-

Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, United States

Post-Doctoral Fellow, Center for Inter-American Policy & Research (CIPR), 2017 - June 2018

Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ, United States

Teaching Assistant, 2014-2017

Non-Academic Employment

Departamento Provincial Santiago Sur, Ministry of Education (Chile)

Chief of Staff, 2012.

Office of Rep. Cristian Monckeberg (23rd District, Chile)

Constituent Services, 2011.

United Nations Development Programme (Santiago, Chile)

Internship, 2010.

Part Time Consultant (different projects)

Data analyst and coordinator, 2006-2011.

Public Outreach

American Political Science Association (APSA): 2016.

Midwest Political Science Association (MPSA): 2017, 2018 (declined).

Latin American Studies Association (LASA): 2014, 2015 (declined), 2016, 2018.

Western Political Science Association (WPSA): 2015, 2016, 2018 (declined).

Southern Political Science Association (SPSA): 2015, 2018.

Development Economics and Policy Conference (German Economic Association): Zurich (2018, declined).

New Frontiers in Clientelism. Guest Lecture. Tulane University, 2017.

Training

1. Tulane University:

• "Introduction to Comparative Politics" (Instructor, undergraduate, spring: 2018).

2. Rutgers University:

- "Math and Computing Camp for Political Scientists" (Instructor, graduate, winter: 2015).
- "Introduction to Quantitative Methods" (TA, graduate, fall: 2015).
- "American Government" (TA, undergraduate, fall: 2014 to spring: 2017).

Funds Granted as a Principal Investigator

Domestic and International Conference Travel Support:

Department of Political Science and School of Arts and Sciences, Rutgers University (both fall and spring awards in 2013, 2014, 2015 and 2016).

Stone Center for Latin American Studies, Tulane University (2017).

Center for Inter-American Policy and Research, Tulane University (2018).

Teaching Assistantship Appointment. *Department of Political Science* and *School of Arts and Sciences*, Rutgers University (2015, 2016, 2017).

Small Grant Fund for Research on Latin America. *Center for Latin American Studies*, Rutgers University (2013).

Teaching Assistant Professional Development Fund. *School for Arts and Sciences*, Rutgers University (2015, 2016, 2017).

Pre-Dissertation Award. Department of Political Science, Rutgers University (2016).

Experimental Workshop Award. *Center for the Experimental Study of Politics and Psychology, Rutgers University* (2015).

Jerome M. Clubb Scholarship. Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research (2013).

Excellence Fellowship. *School for Arts and Sciences*, Rutgers University (2012). Tuition remission, health benefits and stipends, for five years of doctoral studies.

Academic Overview

Research Interest

Comparative political economy, economic and political development, Latin American politics, causal inference, experimental methods and quantitative methods.

Dissertation

My dissertation argues that sectoral economic conflicts fostered state-building in Latin America. Using fine-grained historical case study comparisons, sectoral outputs from 1900 to the present, panel data and time-series econometric techniques, and a novel earthquake dataset (to measure state capacities), I find that industrial expansion altered the post-colonial political balance, thus putting heavy pressures for the implementation of tax institutions. In turn, fiscal expansion fostered both political development and economic growth.

Creative Writing

- Income Taxation and State Capacities in Chile: Measuring Institutional Development Using Historical Earthquake Data, *in preparation*. Lead paper.
- Sectoral Origins of Income Taxation: Industrial Development in Latin America, and The Case of Chile (1900-2010), *under review, Journal of Politics In Latin America*.
- Aiming Right at You: Group v. Individual Clientelistic Targeting in Brazil, revise and resubmit, Journal of Politics in Latin America.
- Still for Sale: The Micro-Dynamics of Vote-Selling in the United States, Evidence From a List Experiment, *in preparation*.
- Structural Transformations and State Institutions in Latin America, 1900-2010, in preparation.
- Testing the Online Model of Candidate Evaluation in a More Realistic Environment, *in preparation*. With Richard Lau (Rutgers) and Mona Kleinberg (UMass Lowell).
- Inclusive Institutions, Unequal Outcomes: Democracy, State Infrastructural Power and Inequality 1970-2015, *in preparation*. With Mart Trasberg (Tulane).
- El Secreto de mi Éxito: Parte II. Los Caminos a Valparaíso en 2009. Revista de Ciencia Política. 31(2), 285-310, 2011. With Pilar Giannini, Juan Pablo Luna, Rodolfo López, Martín Ordoñez and Gonzalo Recart.

Chapters

• ¿Estable Pero Sin Raíces? Los Partidos Políticos Chilenos en la Opinión Pública, in *Cultura Política de la Democracia en Chile, Ch. IX, LAPOP Country Report, 2010*. With Juan Pablo Luna, Germán Bidegain, Roody Reserve and Giancarlo Visconti.

Misc

Skills

Trained as an academic, I have considerable experience as an independent critical person, used to work under pressure, and goal-oriented. Not only I have good writing/analytical skills, but also excellent interpersonal relationships. Having both excellent leadership skills, and willingness to collaborate with others, make me an ideal candidate to take different roles, for instance in different projects, in the same institution. Finally, I have vast experience conducting data/statistical analyses, IRB applications (for my own experiments), and grant writing.

Languages

English, Spanish (native).

Software

R, Stata, LATEX.

Methods Proficiency

Time Series I (ICPSR), Introduction to Bayesian Analysis (ICPSR), Time Series II (ICPSR), Advanced MLE - Panel Data (ICPSR), Experimental Political Science (RU), Advanced Research in Political Economy (RU), Formal Modeling I (Princeton), Advanced Econometrics (RU, Economics), Introduction to Game Theory (ICPSR), Regression III: Advanced Methods (ICPSR), Measurement, Scaling and Dimensional Analysis (ICPSR), Causal Inference for the Social Sciences (ICPSR), Regression Analysis (RU, Statistics), Maximum Likelihood Estimation for GLMs (RU).